I responded, 'What you're saying is...'
然后再加上滋滋滋Z我说了
I'm saying you actually don't understand the difference between individualism and selfishness.
我说你其实不明白个人主义跟自私自利
They are two different things.
那是两码事
Let me start by saying,
首先来讲话
The debate over individualism and collectivism in our country
咱们国家对于个人主义和集体主义的这个争论
I recommend everyone to read Hayek's 'The Road to Serfdom'.
我建议大家去看看哈耶克的通向奴役之路啊
When it comes to collectivism and such concepts,
我对集体主义这些东西来讲的话
I'm not particularly fond of them.
不是特别的感冒
We have our DPRK friend here to keep things in check.
咱们有这个DPRK这老兄这边坐镇的
So, to put it this way,
所以来讲的话
We talk about the period after Reform and Opening up,
我们说改革开放以后的
Chinese society has been very vibrant and prosperous.
中国社会是非常的欣欣向荣的
Recently, we have a new topic on the table,
特别我们最近有一个新议题
which is how to manage the new relationship between China and the U.S.
就是中美的这个新的这种关系应该怎么搞啊
Our country has actually set the tone in this area
咱们国家其实已经在这方面定调了
We hope everyone can talk more about the good things between China and the U.S.
希望大家说更多的中美之间的美好的
Friendly stories
友好的故事
We don’t want to keep stirring up such confrontations
不希望总是搞这种啊这种对抗啊
Or divisions
分裂呀
This competition of ideologies
这种意识形态的这种竞争啊
This type of person doesn't like to get involved in such things.
这类不喜欢搞这种事情啊
Everything should be prioritized based on the bigger picture
一切以大局为重
We should still focus more on telling positive stories between China and the U.S. Especially recently, with the major confrontation between China and the U.S. people have found that the people on both sides can be friendly to each other. When we talk about Western civilization, It's a place where individualism is highly prevalent.
咱们还是应该多讲好中美之间的故事 特别是最近中美大对仗 大家发现这个人民之间是可以友好起来 然后我们说西方文明 它就是一个个人主义非常盛行的一个地方
Some people say,
然后有人说啊
these individuals are selfish and self-centered.
这个些个人就是自私自利呀
How so?
就是怎么样
They don’t take care of the collective.
就是不照顾集体
In what ways?
就是怎么怎么着
I'm asking you, what should modern society look like?
我问你现代社会应该是什么样的
And how did the prototype of modern society come about?
现代社会的雏形又是怎么来的呢
It all started with the development of individualism.
其实都是从个人主义发展开始的
We talk about individualism
我们说个人主义
Humanism
人文主义
Individualism,
Individualism
many things aren't simply equated with others.
很多东西不是跟一些东西就划等号
It's not just about taking care of ourselves,
不是说我们照顾了自己
we also explore the direction in which individuals should develop.
我们研究了个人应该向什么地方发展
We won't be catering to the group anymore
我们就不照顾集体了
On the contrary, if you don't understand your own worth
相反如果一个人你不明白自己存在的价值
You can't maximize the value of your life
你不能把自己的人生的价值发挥到最大
How can you take care of others then?
你又怎么能照顾到别人呢
Right?
对不对
So many Chinese people live their entire lives in the shadow of others
所以很多中国人一辈子活在别人的阴影之下
Living in the shadow of their own parents
活在自己的父母的阴影之下
Living under the judgment of others
活在别人的评价之下
Always thinking about this, isn't it?
活在总是想这个是吧
To return home in glory
衣锦还乡
Always wanting to stand out
总是想出人头地
Then fearing what others might say So life becomes exhausting You'll find that within the social consciousness of a small peasant society, Those feudal notions Many things are not worth promoting Because it used to be a rural society Your travel was slow with carriages and horses
然后又人言可畏 所以活着就很累 你会发现其实小农社会意识当中 封建社会那种东西 很多东西都是不值得推销的 因为以前是个乡土社会啊 你有车马很慢啊
A letter can be cherished for a lifetime.
一封信可以看一辈子
When it comes to many things,
很多东西来讲的话
they don't move at the fast pace of modern society.
不是像现代社会这么快节奏
In the context of living in a modern big city,
而在现代社会大城市生活来讲的话
an individual can feel insignificant in a city.
一个人他在一个城市当中无足轻重
After all, Beijing has over 30 million people.
你说北京有3000多万人呢
What am I, Rongzhen, in comparison?
啊我荣镇算得上什么呢
Right?
对不对
So many things are like this.
所以很多东西就是这样
Being a web celebrity in a big city is somewhat insignificant.
在大城市当中当个网红一点就是无足轻重
But in a smaller place,
但是你在小地方啊
if someone becomes famous,
如果出一个什么名人的话
everyone pays a lot of attention.
就大家都特别重视
That's how it is.
就是这样
So many people
所以很多人
wonder why web celebrities don't want to stay in Beijing anymore,
为什么网红他不愿意在北京继续待着
they prefer to return to their hometowns,
他愿意回到家乡
or move to smaller cities.
回到地方或者去第三城市
That's how it is.
都是这样啊
Many Beijing UPloaders have moved to Shanghai since then.
很多的北京的up主后来都搬到上海了嘛
Exactly.
就是这样
Because in Beijing, you don't stand out.
因为在北京来讲显不着你啊
There are so many talented people in Beijing.
那北京的能人巧匠多了去了
Right?
对不对
So often we talk about individualism
所以很多时候我们说个人主义
You improve yourself.
你完善自己
The pursuit of self-improvement
完善自我的追求
The commonly mentioned Taoist philosophy cultivating immortality and spiritual practice making oneself better you will understand only when you are well can others be well because we judge others by our own standards many things are hard to gauge
常说的道家的思想 修仙修真修行 把自己弄得很好 你就明白了 只有自己好 别人才能好 因为是以己度人 很多东西是看不准的
in addition to our rural society
再加上我们的乡土社会中
Many small farmers have a rather strong mindset.
很多小农意识真的是比较强
Like what kind of car you drive,
就是说你开什么车啊
what kind of house you live in,
你住什么样的房子
whether you’ve renovated it or not,
装不装修啊
what clothes you wear,
穿的衣服怎么怎么样
all these things are for show,
这些东西都是给别人看的
not a reflection of your true inner feelings.
不是自己内心真实的感受
Even your child’s academic performance,
包括你孩子的学习成绩
and how much money you make.
包括你挣多少钱
So, it's that time of the year again for our annual celebration
所以来讲又到了咱们一年的过年
This period
这个阶段
I want to share with everyone
我就跟大家说
the comparison thief of joy
comparison of the thief of joy啊
comparing these things can rob you of all your joy
就是你比较的这些东西呢会让你的乐趣啊全无
you keep comparing yourself with others
你天天跟人比啊
I have 600,000 followers.
我有60万粉丝啊
I have one million followers, you know, one million.
人家有100万粉丝呢啊等下100万啊
I still have three million followers.
人家还有300万粉丝呢
Let's aim for 3 million followers.
等到300万粉丝啊
There are still 10 million followers.
还有1000万粉丝呢
You're always comparing
你天天比
Then what about the achievements you've made
那你取得的成就又算什么呢
Do you have to be the top to feel good
啊难道非得是你都当了第一了
Only then do you feel satisfied
你就感觉很好
I was the first person on Bilibili to receive the Power Up badge.
那我是B站第一个获得充电奖牌的人
Should I be overjoyed
难道我就应该很高兴吗
Should I be complacent
沾沾自喜吗
It's not about being arrogant in victory or dejected in defeat I've been telling you this every day What's going on with you You should be modest and cautious Not proud or impatient And when you're happy about your achievements You shouldn't be unhappy Someone else might have achieved even more than you
不是胜不骄败不馁 天天跟你说啊 你这个怎么着 应该谦虚谨慎 不骄不躁 然后你高兴你取得什么成就 你也不高兴啊 你取得的成就有人比你取得更大的成就
You shouldn't let that make you unhappy
你也不高兴起来
I got accepted into Renmin University.
我考上人大了
But you know, some people get into Tsinghua or Peking University.
是不是哎结果人家还有清华北大呢
You'll find that your parents,
你就会发现你的家长
and the people around you all have this kind of mindset,
还有周围的这些人都是这种思想
this elitist way of thinking.
就是这种优寄主义的思想
Coupled with a deeply ingrained peasant mentality, it's really scary.
再加上小农意识非常可怕哦
If I don't become the top student,
我不当状元
then I'm not cut out for academics in this life.
这辈子就不是读书人了啊
I won't be the champion.
我不当冠军
I guess I'm not destined to be a sports star in this life.
这辈子就不是体育明星了啊
I can only do the bare minimum, then.
我就只能跳擦边了
Is that how it is?
是这么回事吗
Oh, is that how it is?
啊是这么回事吗
Is that how the world works?
这世界是这样的吗
The world is full of diversity.
这世界是丰富多彩的
The world offers many opportunities to many people.
这世界是给很多人很多的机会的
So, in the context of the past,
所以说在过去那种语境下
suppress individualism
打压个人主义
suppress Humanism
打压人文主义
Suppressing the humanities
打压文科
Suppressing this thing
打压这东西
That's taking the old Soviet path
那就是走苏联的老路
It's completely useless
一点没用
The Soviet Union is gone
苏联没了
The Soviet Union collapsed
苏联垮了
The Soviet Union no longer exists
苏联不存在了啊
Think more clearly
想明白点
Don't swerve so much.
别左的那么厉害
Think deeply about what's really going on with you.
想细想自己到底是怎么回事
Why did you do that?
为什么要那样
Why?
为什么
Now, let me tell you.
现在我跟你说
Pure science can't solve sociological issues. Humanistic elements. The spirit. The spiritual pursuits of the people. Only the humanities can solve it Such as sociology Political science historiography And international relations We didn't pay enough attention to these in the past
重理科解决不了社会的社会学问题 人文的东西 精神 人民群众的精神追求问题 只能用人文科学来解决 就是社会学 政治学 历史学 国际关系学这些东西来讲 咱过去重视的太少了
Including social psychology
包括社会心理学性
These fields like sociology should be studied
社会学这些东西都是应该研究的
If you don't study them, others' external theories will take over
你不研究这些让别人的外力学说占住了啊
the upper hand in the public opinion field
舆论场的上风
Is that possible?
那能行吗
Right?
对不对
So we deal with a few boxing influencers
于是解决几个打拳的博主
Can the birth rate really bounce back?
这个出生率就能回来的吗
Is that how it works?
是这么回事吗
It's not that we overly emphasize collectivism all the time.
不是所以很多的时候我们就太重集体主义了
Not focused on individualism
不重个人主义
Individualism should be developed alongside collectivism.
个人主义是应该同集体主义同时发展的
Neither idealism nor materialism is entirely correct.
就像唯心跟唯物都不对
It should be the path of moderation and balance.
其实应该是中和中庸之道
So I really dislike Confucianism.
所以我很讨厌儒家
But the doctrine of the mean is not wrong.
但是中庸之道没错
The doctrine of the mean is absolutely correct.
中庸之道是一点没错
Inclusiveness and diversity.
兼容并包
Sino-American cooperation can achieve great things.
中美合作可以做很大的事情
The humanities and sciences can sit side by side.
文理之间携手而坐
Can we integrate Eastern and Western knowledge?
能不能学贯中西
Can we avoid overemphasizing literature?
能不能不重文
Or overemphasizing rituals?
也不重礼
We should balance literature and science.
文理兼修啊
Can we take the best from both China and the U.S.?
能不能中美之间的各取取长补短
In fact, The New China also learned from the Soviet Union. and also from the United States. We've learned a lot. Many aspects of the Reform and Opening up have been learned from the West for a long time. We learned a lot during the New Culture Movement era.
其实我们新中国是又学了苏联 又学了美国的东西 学了很多东西啊 改革开放很多东西跟人西方学了很久了 我们以前新文化运动的时候就学了很多
In the past, the United States was seen as a relatively good example among Western powers.
以前是拿美利坚合众国当成是西方列强
a relatively positive state.
一个相对比较好的一个状态的
Right?
是不是
So, we shouldn't overcorrect on so many things.
所以很多东西不要那么矫枉过正
We shouldn’t think about everything in such a way.
一切东西都想的啊
Always causing trouble with others.
整天就是跟人怎么闹
Going down together in a blaze of glory.
那个玉石俱焚
And then making it impossible to get along with others.
然后再怎么着就跟人家过不下去了
Just part ways.
就就就一一拍两散了
Is that how he lives?
他是那样的生活吗
Is that the culture?
是那样的文化吗
So many things are like this.
所以我们很多东西就是这样
I said it.
我说了
We need to read Marx,
既要读马克思
and also take industry courses.
也要读行业课啊
Each has its limitations.
都有局限性
Each has its historical context.
都有时代背景
Only by deeply Sinicizing it,
只有把他深刻的中国化啊
We'll proceed based on our realistic approach.
按照我们的现实主义的东西进行啊
The various lessons and experiences from the Chinese revolution are also important.
中国革命的思想的各种各样的经验教训也好
We need to revise them before moving forward.
把它修正以后再去那什么
Of course.
当然来讲
Can you just read Hayek?
你光看哈耶克行吗
Just reading Hayek suggests that the market is the solution to all problems.
光看哈耶克市场是解决一切的问题的标准
That's it.
那那完了
The United States today is following Hayek's path.
那美国今天呢就是按哈耶克的路在走
Right?
对不对
And when it comes to collectivism, there are certain aspects to consider. if it ends up like the Soviet Union is that really right? The economy also collapsed, which was clearly wrong So, we shouldn’t overcorrect you shouldn’t lean too far left
而且集体主义有些东西来讲 搞成苏联那样子来讲 难道就是对的吗 经济也搞崩了也是不对的呀 所以矫枉不能过正 你左右既不要左
or too far right
也不要右
be moderate
中庸一点
listen to both sides, focus on both technology and spirit
两边的话都听既修科技也修精神啊
Cultivating and advancing in technology can go hand in hand.
修仙跟攀科技树两不误
Balancing arts and sciences is important.
文理两不误
We can excel in both China and the U.S.
中美两开花
No problem at all.
没问题的
Right?
对不对
We're not planning to film Journey to the West.
咱们又不是要拍西游记
That's just how many things work.
很多东西就是这样
So we shouldn't overcorrect.
所以咱们矫枉不能过正
Some things are just like that.
有些东西就是这样
We can't say it's for collectivism.
不能说为了集体主义
We completely abandon individualism.
我们个人主义完全不要了
and individuals just fade away
个人完全就消消失掉
That's not the case
那不是啊
If you're from the seventies
那你是七零后
or the sixties
六零后
you can do that
你可以这么干
or the eighties
八零后
or the nineties
九零后
Can the post-00s really do that?
零零后能这么干吗
Right?
对不对
The post-80s are the generation bridging the gap.
八零后承上启下的一代
We've really had it tough.
我们算他妈遭了殃了
We actually get the most criticism.
我们其实挨着最大的骂
And we didn't get to enjoy much good stuff.
然后没什么好东西没赶上
The post-90s.
九零后
The post-00s don't have to carry that burden anymore.
零零后其实已经不用背
They don't have to bear that weight.
人家不用背这种包袱啊
Why should anyone carry the burden of history?
人家干嘛要背历史包袱呢
Right?
对不对
They have a new starting point.
人家有新的起点
A new beginning is just like that.
新的出发就是这样
As he grew up, China had already become strong. Of course, he doesn’t have to carry it. All the scar literature from the Heshang generation He doesn't need to He's starting anew He's different In today's China
他成长的时候 中国已经强大了 他当然不用去背啊 合商那一代的所有所有的那些伤痕文学的东西 他不需要 他是重新出发的 他不一样 所以在当今中国来讲
We talk about a hundred schools of thought contending
我们说百家争鸣
A hundred flowers blooming is the best
百花齐放是最好的
When it comes to many things
其实很多东西来讲
You are in America.
你在美国
There are certain things you really can't do
你有些事情确实是不能干
It can't be said that criticism is off-limits
不能说不能批评
because of the banner of political correctness
因为有政治正确大旗
there's also PC
也有PC啊
right?
对不对
Moving on
再来讲的话
but it's not the case here
但是我们这边不行
PC is illegal here
我们这边PC是违法的
so a lot of things are like this
所以很多东西就是这样啊
there's not much overly controversial stuff to talk about
没有什么太过分的东西去讨论
There's nothing too special about it
没有什么太那什么
Of course, if you raise a big banner
当然你要竖起一面大旗来
there will definitely be people who attack you
就肯定会有人攻击你
but regardless
但无论如何
Individualism is not a bad thing.
个人主义不是一件坏事
developing oneself has never been a bad thing
发展自我也从来不是一件坏事
it's always been like that
都是这样
Hayek
哈耶克
he emphasized some of his ideas from his time
他讲究的是那个时代的他的一些思想
So you need to understand his things to be inclusive
所以你要看他的的东西就能兼容并包
So everyone must understand
所以我跟大家一定要明白
We must understand both heaven and hell
一定要天堂与地狱都要明白
We must understand the religions of all places
一定要各个的地方的宗教
So, you dislike religion.
也就是你不喜欢宗教
You should study religion even more
那你就更要研究宗教啊
You dislike history You should study history You dislike these humanities subjects You should focus on the humanities. You have a good grasp of both areas. Skills never weigh you down. But it’s not enough to dabble in them.
你不喜欢历史 你就要研究历史 你不喜欢这些文科的东西 你就要研究文科的东西 你两个东西都掌握了啊 需艺不压身 学艺不精
Sometimes you need to apply engineering thinking to solve social issues.
有的时候你用工程学的思维去解决社会问题
Would that work?
那能行吗
That would be chaos.
那不都乱套了
Many issues involve public sentiment.
很多人心向背的问题
It's essential to be familiar with communication studies.
必须要熟悉传播学
Journalism
新闻学
some aspects of psychology
心理学的一些东西
especially some aspects of sociology
特别是社会学的一些东西
you can truly encounter
你能真正遇到
you can't just say anything
你不能说什么东西啊
Let's come up with an algorithm
咱们弄一个算法
and then eliminate those below 84%
然后再低于什么84%的人
We'll all get rid of them
咱们都杀掉
Is that how it works?'
那是这么回事吗
Is that right?
对不对
So, when it comes to some things,
所以有些东西来讲
we shouldn't overcorrect,
不能去矫枉过正
using these methods to tackle every problem.
去用这些方法去对付所有的问题
Speaking of the cooperation between China and the U.S. today,
就是咱们今天说的这个中美之间合作
there's a lot that can be done.
是可以做很多的事情
There are many wonderful stories to tell.
有很多美好的故事可以去讲述
For many people, the U.S. is a completely different place,
很多人对美国来讲是一个完完全全的一个啊
and today, let's talk about it.
其实其实在今天来说说
Chinese people are quite familiar with American culture.
中国老百姓对美国的文化是很了解的
When it comes to its culture and geography, many aspects are well-known.
他的文化它的地理很多东西来讲
Through cultural exports, there's a good understanding of it.
通过他的文化输出是很了解的
Many aspects of the other side are known.
是对方很多东西
Like today, for example. There are many things on Xiaohongshu. People are starting to make egg custard now. Soy sauce is even sold out. They're also beginning to learn how to make tofu with green onions. Learning how to make braised pork is also a good idea. This is a good thing.
你像今天啊 就像小红书上很多东西 人家现在开始开始做鸡蛋羹了啊 酱油也卖脱了啊 这个小葱拌豆腐也这个这个开始学起来了 红烧肉也学起来 这就是好事
So, when it comes to many things,
所以很多东西来讲
you need to take the puzzle piece from others,
就是你要把别人那块拼图拿过来
only by bringing the flat head over,
只有把平头拿过来
walk on two legs,
两条腿走路
read with both hands,
两只手看书啊
can this issue be resolved.
这个问题才能
Don't always promote your stuff just for the sake of it.
那东西你不要老是因为为了宣传你的这些东西
Conducting propaganda
搞宣教
Engaging in public opinion warfare is pointless.
搞这个舆论战没有意思
You need to thoroughly understand what others have
你只有把别人的东西啊
Or rather, what your enemies have
或者说敌人的东西都研究透了
Take our current attitude toward Japan
你说我们今天对日本
What about the generation born in the 2000s
那零零后
Why are those born in the 1990s also interested in Japan?
九零后对日本为什么也趣味了呢
Because they have visited Japan multiple times
因为去的次数多了
And they have learned the Japanese language
日语的东西会了
Life in Japan has changed
日本生活过了
So many people have developed an interest in Japan
所以很多人对日本就趣味了
It's connected to the bubble economy of the 1970s and 80s
他跟七八十年代去日本泡沫经济
People who went to work there during that time
那时代去那打工的人
Can we think the same way?
那是能一样的思维吗
Of course, it's a different story
当然是不一样的事
Today's international students are different from those 20 years ago
今天的留学生跟我们20年前的留学生
They are not the same
也不一样
Today's students are more confident
今天留学生更自信啊
It feels even better I started eating right away when I got back Back then, you see I didn’t really notice much difference in the food after I went out It was just cooking for myself over there Right? But it’s not like today’s production The material life is so abundant now
更加的感觉非常好 一回来就哐哐炫饭 我们那时候来讲的话 出去以后也没觉得吃的差别有多大 也就是在那边自己做饭 对不对 但是没有今天似的这个生产 生活物质这么丰富啊
Back then, I thought learning a few Western dishes was quite fun
那时候倒觉得学几套西餐也挺好玩的
That was just how things were back then.
那个时候就是那样
The development gap in life was huge back then.
那个时候的生活发展差异太大了
So the disparities persist to this day.
所以到今天差异也大
But the roles have reversed in many aspects.
但就是攻守转换了更多的东西来讲
It's completely different now.
完完全全不一样
So we can say that today we have a thoroughly new
所以我们说今天我们有一个完完全全的一个
cultural confidence.
文化上的自信
Don't be so
不要那么的啊
Like a dagger to one's pride
匕首自尊似的
Don't be so uptight
不要那么着哈
Progress step by step
步步开放
A very conservative state
很保守的状态
That's not the case
那不是的
Move forward
往前走
Stride forward boldly
大踏步的向前
Tackle problems as they arise
有问题再解决问题
Don't worry about potential issues
不要担心会出现问题
If there's a problem, solve it, and everything will be fine.
有问题解决问题就没有事儿
No day is the end of the world
哪一天也不是世界末日
We need to have confidence.
就要有一种自信啊
But not a blind confidence.
跟一种盲目的自信
It's like water without a source.
这东西就是无根之水
A very important person.
很重要的人
Development works the same way.
发展也是这样
No matter what opinion you express.
无论你提出什么样的言论
I'll be fine.
我怎么样
There will definitely be people who criticize you
肯定会有人骂你
Just like I mentioned in my last video It's been 26 years I finally understand myself No one will love me anymore, and so on Then many people read the title Read a couple of sentences Come in to criticize Say what they think Or someone comes to wish me well
你就像我上一期我说啊 26年了 我终于明白了自己 这个这个这个这个这个不会有人爱我了之类 然后很多人看个标题啊 看两句话啊 进来骂一下 说一下就是什么 或者还有人来祝福我
I think that's pretty funny
那我觉得就挺搞笑的
You know
你知道吗
I'm just using this question to expand my thinking.
因为我只是在对这个问题用来展开我的思维
What kind of things do I observe?
我的所观察到的东西是什么样的
I really need some love
我真缺爱啊
Just do it
做就完了嘛
Right?
对不对
You don't have to worry about so many new things
就不用担心那么多新的
I'm not really lacking
我不是真缺缺的
With you guys, I'm not lacking
是你们我不缺
Those are the people I was talking about who left the comments.
那就是我说的那些评论的人啊
How could I be lacking?
就是我怎么缺呢
I've always been practicing in real situations
我一直都是在实践当中
How so?
怎么怎么
So how could I possibly be lacking?
所以怎么可能缺呢
Exactly, it's like Sima Zhao's intentions, right?
就是啊司马昭之心嘛
That's just how things are
很多东西就是这样
So don't judge by appearances
所以就是不要拿表面上的东西
That's not people's real thoughts
当当人们真的的思维
That's the way it is
这是那么回事
Because I'm doing a show
因为我要做节目
I definitely need to open up my mind
我做节目肯定要展开思想
I have to put myself in the character's shoes
把自己带入到人物当中去
I need to become that character
我要成为那个角色
I need to embody the state of someone who doesn't get love
我要成为那个得不到爱的那个状态的人
So this is a kind of performance. It's a reenactment of a scenario. It's also a way to put ourselves in others' shoes and discuss these issues together. It's not that I actually have these problems myself. I might not be able to delve deeply into these issues either.
所以这就是一种表演 这是一种情景的再现啊 这也是一种设身处地的跟大家去讨论这种问题 并不是我真正我要是真正有这方面问题 我也会不会能够对这些问题有一个深入的讨论
So, up to today.
所以就是到今天为止
Don't really think that others...
很多东西就是不要真觉得别人啊
Will definitely have some issue.
一定会出什么问题
Before they would discuss it with you.
才会跟你去讨论
These things
这些东西
It's not really because there's a principle in communication studies.
其实也不并不是因为传播学有一个道理
which is that you need to position yourself in a relatively humble place
就是你一定要把自己放在一个比较低的位置
you have to be the clown in society
你要去做社会当中这个小丑
the one who is seen as funny by everyone
你要去做这个大家的眼中的这个搞笑的
that person
这个人啊
the one in an awkward situation
这个处境窘态的这个人
This aligns with the principles of communication studies.
这是符合传播学的规律的
you don't necessarily have to be a one-to-one replica in real life
你未必真的需要是现实中真的一比一
Exact replica
原原班复制
That's how it is
就是这样的
So we often say that we shouldn't create confrontation
所以我们经常说很多东西就是不要去搞对抗
We should look for common ground
多去找共同点
Don't argue until you're red in the face
不要去找跟人家争得脸红
Or until your neck is stiff
脖子粗的东西
We should seek resonance
多要去找一些共鸣
In the process, discover new opportunities
在找的过程中发现新的机会
And make new friends along the way
在找的过程中结交新的朋友
I highly recommend everyone to visit Xiao Hong's Study Room
我特别推荐大家去小红书房
Now, chat more with foreigners Check the accounts Talk about what we lack compared to others We can also check and compare But more often, it’s that others might suddenly find their wall has fallen An information gap appears
现在多跟老外聊一聊啊 对一对账啊 聊一聊自己不如别人的东西呢 咱们也可以对一对 但是更多来讲是别人可能突然之间他那墙倒了 他信息差出现了
They realize
他才发现
That the Chinese people are not actually living in such dire straits
其实中国人民根本就没有那么水深火热
In dire straits
水深火热
It’s actually quite amusing
是自己其实就挺逗的
But we have some things here too
但是呢咱们这边呢也有一些东西呢
That can be learned from developed countries, which is quite different
其实可以跟一些发达国家借鉴是完全不一样的
So our main focus should be on liberating our own minds
所以我们主要是在于解放我们自己的思想
Liberating our own minds
我们解放我们自己的思想
Is not about saving someone or becoming one of them
并不是为了去救和谁去成为他们当中的一员
It’s not about standing alone
不是我们自己自成一极
These things are all about confidence
所以这些东西来讲就是一种自信啊
But I suggest you don’t set up
但是我建议大家呢不要去竖起啊
How should I put this
这个这个怎么说呢
A strong barrier, like Trump
这个坚强壁垒真跟川普似的
Building a border wall
弄个边境墙啊
Opening up and allowing visa-free entry
打开自己的东西给人免签
No problem
没问题
Let everyone come and see
让大家过来看
Let them see our lives
让大家看看我们的生活
Let them see our thoughts
让大家看看我们的思想
There’s no issue
没有关系的
Correcting wrongs should not go too far
矫枉不能过正
Being well-versed in both Eastern and Western knowledge
学贯中西啊
Balancing humanities and sciences
文理兼修这个东西
Integrating both civil and military aspects
文武一体
This is the best
这是最好的
Because as you can see, in Bagua Tai Chi and all these things
因为你看八卦太极所有的东西来讲
Yin and Yang are in harmonious balance There shouldn’t be so much conflict Always fighting like those in the Middle East That’s not interesting The best is not about heaven and hell Not about rewarding the good and punishing the evil It’s about the fusion of Yin and Yang
阴阳他是调和的平衡 不要有那么多的斗争 整天就那个阿米DIAN就在那打 那没有意思 最好的不是天堂与地狱的 不是什么赏善罚恶 是阴阳融合
The integration of good and evil
善恶一体
This is the essence of human nature
这才是人的一种本质
This is why sometimes I talk about some dark aspects
这也是为什么有时候我会讲一些东西
And then blend them together
会讲到很黑暗的那部分
Because this is a harmonious balance
然后再融合过来
This is what makes it interesting
因为这个东西它是调和的
So today, we’re saying don’t overcorrect
这个东西它才有意思
Don’t use a mindset of struggle
所以咱们就今天说矫枉不要过正
Struggle with everyone
不要用那个斗争的思维啊
Struggle between left and right
跟谁都是斗争啊
Struggle between good and evil
都是左与右的斗争
The struggle between good and evil
善与恶的斗争
To others, they still see it as a step towards good
黑与白的斗争
Then what are you?
那人家看来人家还是善的一步呢
So many things are like this
那你又是什么呢
Don’t always look for confrontation
所以很多东西就是这样
Find more points of agreement
不要永远都是找对抗
Tell the story of Sino-American friendship well
多找一些契合点
Right?
把中美的友谊的故事讲好啊
Welcome President Trump’s visit to China
对不对